Many believe driving is an activity
الكثيرون يعتقدون أن القيادة نشاط
solely reserved for those who can see.
ممكن فقط لأولئك الذين يمكنهم الرؤيه.
A blind person driving a vehicle safely and independently
إن فكرة شخص كفيف يقود مركبة بأمان وبصورة مستقلة
was thought to be an impossible task, until now.
كان يعتقد أنها مهمة مستحيلة، حتى الآن.
Hello, my name is Dennis Hong,
مرحبا، اسمي دنيس كونغ،
and we're bringing freedom and independence to the blind
ونحن نحاول جلب الحرية والاستقلال للمكفوفين
by building a vehicle for the visually impaired.
من خلال بناء سياره لضعاف البصر.
So before I talk about this car for the blind,
حتى قبل أن أتحدث عن هذه السيارة للمكفوفين،
let me briefly tell you about another project that I worked on
اسمحوا لي ان اقول لكم باختصار حول آخر المشاريع التي عملت عليها
called the DARPA Urban Challenge.
يسمى تحدي داربا الحضرى.
Now this was about building a robotic car
الآن كان ذلك نحو بناء سيارة روبوتية
that can drive itself.
يمكن أن تقود نفسها.
You press start, nobody touches anything,
تضغط ابدأ ، لا أحد يمس أي شيء،
and it can reach its destination fully autonomously.
ويمكن أن تصل إلى وجهتها بشكل مستقل تماما.
So in 2007, our team won half a million dollars
ذلك في عام 2007، وفاز فريقنا بنصف مليون دولار
by placing third place in this competition.
من خلال احتلال المركز الثالث في هذه المسابقة.
So about that time,
لذا في حوالي ذلك الوقت،
the National Federation of the Blind, or NFB,
الاتحاد الوطني للمكفوفين، أو NFB،
challenged the research committee
تحدى لجنة البحوث
about who can develop a car
حول من يستطيع تطوير سيارة
that lets a blind person drive safely and independently.
تسمح لشخص كفيف بالقياده بسلام وبشكل مستقل.
We decided to give it a try,
قررنا تجربتها،
because we thought, "Hey, how hard could it be?"
لأننا اعتقدنا، ان الامر لن يكون بهذه الصعوبة.
We have already an autonomous vehicle.
لدينا بالفعل سيارة مستقلة.
We just put a blind person in it and we're done, right?
نضع فقط شخص أعمى فيها و لقد انتهينا، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We couldn't have been more wrong.
نحن لا يمكن أن نكون أكثر خطأ.
What NFB wanted
ما أراد NFB
was not a vehicle that can drive a blind person around,
لم يكن سيارة يمكن تقود شخص كفيف إلي أي مكان،
but a vehicle where a blind person can make active decisions and drive.
ولكن سيارة فيها شخص مكفوف يستطيع اتخاذ قرارات فعالة والقياده.
So we had to throw everything out the window
لذلك وجب علينا رمي كل شيء من النافذة
and start from scratch.
والبدء من الصفر.
So to test this crazy idea,
لذا لاختبار هذه الفكرة المجنونة،
we developed a small dune buggy prototype vehicle
طورنا عربة الكثبان الرملية الصغيرة إلي سيارة النموذج الأولي
to test the feasibility.
لاختبار الجدوى.
And in the summer of 2009,
وفي صيف عام 2009،
we invited dozens of blind youth from all over the country
دعونا العشرات من الشباب المكفوفين من جميع أنحاء البلاد
and gave them a chance to take it for a spin.
وأعطيناهم فرصة تجربة القياده
It was an absolutely amazing experience.
كانت تجربة مدهشة تماما.
But the problem with this car was
ولكن المشكلة مع هذه سيارة
it was designed to only be driven in a very controlled environment,
تم تصميمها لتكون تحت القياده فقط في بيئة محكومة جدا،
in a flat, closed-off parking lot --
في موقف سيارات مغلق ومسطح --
even the lanes defined by red traffic cones.
حتى الممرات يحددها مخاريط حركة المرور الحمراء.
So with this success,
لذا مع هذا النجاح ،
we decided to take the next big step,
قررنا اتخاذ الخطوة التالية الكبيرة،
to develop a real car that can be driven on real roads.
لتطوير سيارة حقيقية يمكن قيادتها على الطرق الحقيقية.
So how does it work?
فكيف تعمل؟
Well, it's a rather complex system,
حسنا ، انه نظام معقد نوعا ما ،
but let me try to explain it, maybe simplify it.
ولكن اسمحوا لي أن أحاول تفسير ذلك، وربما تبسيطه.
So we have three steps.
لذلك لدينا ثلاث خطوات.
We have perception, computation
لدينا التصور والحساب
and non-visual interfaces.
و الواجهات غير المرئية.
Now obviously the driver cannot see,
من الواضح الآن لا يستطيع السائق أن يرى،
so the system needs to perceive the environment
لذا النظام يحتاج إلى إدراك البيئة
and gather information for the driver.
وجمع المعلومات للسائق.
For that, we use an initial measurement unit.
لذلك، نحن نستخدم وحدة قياس أولي.
So it measures acceleration, angular acceleration --
ذلك أنها تقيس التسارع ، التسارع الزاوي --
like a human ear, inner ear.
مثل الأذن البشرية، الأذن الداخلية.
We fuse that information with a GPS unit
نحن نربط تلك المعلومات مع وحدة نظام تحديد المواقع
to get an estimate of the location of the car.
للحصول على تقدير لموقع السيارة.
We also use two cameras to detect the lanes of the road.
ونحن أيضا نستخدم اثنين من الكاميرات للكشف عن مسارات الطريق.
And we also use three laser range finders.
ونحن أيضا نستخدم ثلاث محددات مدى بأشعة الليزر.
The lasers scan the environment to detect obstacles --
الليزر لتفحص البيئة للكشف عن العقبات --
a car approaching from the front, the back
سيارة تقترب من الأمام, من الخلف
and also any obstacles that run into the roads,
وكذلك أي عقبات تتواجد داخل الشوارع،
any obstacles around the vehicle.
أي عقبات في جميع أنحاء السيارة.
So all this vast amount of information is then fed into the computer,
بحيث يتم تغذية كل هذا الكم الهائل من المعلومات في الكمبيوتر،
and the computer can do two things.
ويمكن للكمبيوتر القيام بأمرين.
One is, first of all, process this information
واحد هو، أولا وقبل كل شيء ، معالجة هذه المعلومات
to have an understanding of the environment --
أن يكون هناك فهم للبيئة --
these are the lanes of the road, there's the obstacles --
هذه هي مسارات الطريق، وهناك العقبات --
and convey this information to the driver.
و نقل هذه المعلومات إلى السائق.
The system is also smart enough
هذا النظام هو أيضا ذكي بما فيه الكفاية
to figure out the safest way to operate the car.
لمعرفة الطريق الأسلم لتشغيل السيارة.
So we can also generate instructions
حتى نتمكن من توليد أيضا تعليمات
on how to operate the controls of the vehicle.
حول كيفية تشغيل ضوابط للسيارة.
But the problem is this: How do we convey
لكن المشكلة هي : كيف ننقل
this information and instructions
هذه المعلومات والإرشادات
to a person who cannot see
إلى شخص لا يرى
fast enough and accurate enough so he can drive?
بسرعة كافية ودقيقة بما فيه الكفاية حتى يتمكن من قيادة السيارة؟
So for this, we developed many different types
لذلك ، قمنا بتطوير أنواع مختلفة من
of non-visual user interface technology.
واجهة مستخدم تقنية غير بصرية.
So starting from a three-dimensional ping sound system,
ذلك ابتداء من نظام بينغ الصوت ثلاثي الأبعاد ،
a vibrating vest,
سترة اهتزاز،
a click wheel with voice commands, a leg strip,
عجلة نقر مع الأوامر الصوتية ، شريط ساق,
even a shoe that applies pressure to the foot.
حتى الحذاء الذي يطبق ضغط على الأقدام.
But today we're going to talk about
ولكن اليوم سنقوم بالحديث عن
three of these non-visual user interfaces.
ثلاثة من واجهات المستخدم غير المرئية.
Now the first interface is called a DriveGrip.
الآن تسمى الواجهة الأولى قبضة المحرك.
So these are a pair of gloves,
لذا فإن هذه هي زوج من القفازات،
and it has vibrating elements on the knuckle part
ولها عناصر اهتزازات على جزء المفصل،
so you can convey instructions about how to steer --
حتى تتمكن من نقل الإرشادات حول كيفية توجيه --
the direction and the intensity.
الإتجاه والكثافة.
Another device is called SpeedStrip.
جهاز آخر يسمى قطاع السرعة.
So this is a chair -- as a matter of fact, it's actually a massage chair.
هذا مقعد -- في الواقع، فإنه في الواقع كرسي التدليك.
We gut it out, and we rearrange the vibrating elements in different patterns,
فإننا قمنا بنزعه، وإعادة ترتيب عناصر الاهتزاز في أنماط مختلفة.
and we actuate them to convey information about the speed,
كما أننا قمنا تحفيزها لهم لنقل معلومات بشأن السرعة،
and also instructions how to use the gas and the brake pedal.
وأيضا تعليمات حول كيفية استخدام الغاز ودواسة الفرامل.
So over here, you can see
لذا هنا ، يمكنك ان ترى
how the computer understands the environment,
كيف يتفهم الكمبيوتر البيئة.
and because you cannot see the vibration,
ولأنك لا تستطيع رؤية الاهتزاز،
we actually put red LED's on the driver so that you can see what's happening.
وضعنا فعلا الصمام الثنائي التي ينبعث منها ضوء أحمر على السائق ، حتى يتمكن من رؤية ما يحدث في الواقع.
This is the sensory data,
هذه هي المعطيات الحسية،
and that data is transferred to the devices through the computer.
ويتم نقل هذه البيانات إلى الأجهزة عن طريق الكمبيوتر.
So these two devices, DriveGrip and SpeedStrip,
وبالتالي فإن هذان الجهازان مقبض المحرك وقطاع السرعة ،
are very effective.
فعالان جداً
But the problem is
ولكن المشكلة هي
these are instructional cue devices.
أن هذه أجهزة اشارة تعليمية.
So this is not really freedom, right?
هذه ليست حقا حرية، أليس كذلك؟
The computer tells you how to drive --
الكمبيوتر يوضح لك كيفية القيادة --
turn left, turn right, speed up, stop.
انعطف يسارا، يمينا، واسرع، وقف.
We call this the "backseat-driver problem."
نحن ندعو هذه مشكلة سائق المقعد الخلفي.
So we're moving away from the instructional cue devices,
لذلك نحن نتحرك بعيدا عن أجهزة الاشارة التعليمية،
and we're now focusing more
ونحن نركز الآن أكثر
on the informational devices.
على الأجهزة الإعلامية.
A good example for this informational non-visual user interface
وخير مثال لهذه الواجهة للمستخدم الإعلامية غير المرئية
is called AirPix.
ويسمى بيكسل الهواء.
So think of it as a monitor for the blind.
لذا فكر في أنها كما لو كانت شاشة للمكفوفين.
So it's a small tablet, has many holes in it,
لذلك فهي لوحة صغيرة ، وبها الكثير من الثقوب،
and compressed air comes out,
والهواء المضغوط يخرج،
so it can actually draw images.
بحيث يمكن رسم صور في الواقع .
So even though you are blind, you can put your hand over it,
لذا حتى ولو كنت أعمى ، يمكنك وضع يدك عليها،
you can see the lanes of the road and obstacles.
تستطيع أن ترى في مسارات الطريق والعقبات.
Actually, you can also change the frequency of the air coming out
في الواقع، يمكنك أيضا تغيير وتيرة خروج الهواء
and possibly the temperature.
وربما درجة الحرارة.
So it's actually a multi-dimensional user interface.
لذا فإنه في الواقع واجهة مستخدم متعددة الأبعاد.
So here you can see the left camera, the right camera from the vehicle
بحيث يمكنك هنا ان ترى الكاميرا اليسرى والكاميرا اليمنى من السيارة
and how the computer interprets that and sends that information to the AirPix.
وكيف يفسر ذلك الكمبيوتر ويرسل تلك المعلومات إلى بيكسل الهواء.
For this, we're showing a simulator,
لهذا، ونحن نبدي جهاز محاكاة،
a blind person driving using the AirPix.
لقيادة شخص كفيف باستخدام بيكسل الهواء.
This simulator was also very useful for training the blind drivers
وكان هذا أيضا جهاز محاكاة مفيد جدا لتدريب السائقين المكفوفين
and also quickly testing different types of ideas
وكذلك لاختبار بسرعة أنواع مختلفة من الأفكار
for different types of non-visual user interfaces.
لأنواع مختلفة من واجهات المستخدم غير المرئية.
So basically that's how it works.
هذه في الأساس هي الطريقة التي يعمل بها.
So just a month ago,
ذلك قبل شهر فقط
on January 29th,
يوم 29 يناير،
we unveiled this vehicle for the very first time to the public
كشفنا النقاب عن هذه السيارة للمرة الأولى أمام الجمهور
at the world-famous Daytona International Speedway
في مضمار دايتونا العالمي الشهير لسباق الدراجات النارية
during the Rolex 24 racing event.
خلال هذا الحدث سباقات رولكس 24.
We also had some surprises. Let's take a look.
كان لدينا أيضا بعض المفاجآت. دعونا نلقي نظرة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Announcer: This is an historic day in January.
(فيديو) المذيع : هذا يوم تاريخي
He's coming up to the grandstand, fellow Federationists.
انه قادم الى المدرج الزميل فيديرستاس.
(Cheering)
(هتاف)
(Honking)
(التزمير)
There's the grandstand now.
هناك المدرج الآن.
And he's [unclear] following that van that's out in front of him.
وانه يقود و يتجاوز تلك الشاحنة من أمامه.
Well there comes the first box.
حسنا ها هو الصندوق الاول
Now let's see if Mark avoids it.
الآن دعونا نرى ما اذا كان مارك تيمكن من تجنبه.
He does. He passes it on the right.
يفعل. إنه يمر على اليمين.
Third box is out. The fourth box is out.
المربع الثالث خارج. المربع الرابع خارج.
And he's perfectly making his way between the two.
وانه جعل تماما طريقه بينهما .
He's closing in on the van
انه مقتربا منا على الشاحنة
to make the moving pass.
لإجراء مرور الحركة.
Well this is what it's all about,
حسنا هذا هو ما يدور حوله كل الأمر,
this kind of dynamic display of audacity and ingenuity.
هذا النوع من العرض الديناميكي من الجرأة والإبداع.
He's approaching the end of the run,
انه يقترب من نهاية السباق،
makes his way between the barrels that are set up there.
يشق طريقه بين البراميل التي تقام هناك.
(Honking)
(تزمير)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Dennis Hong: I'm so happy for you.
دنيس كونج : أنا سعيد جدا لك.
Mark's going to give me a ride back to the hotel.
مارك سوف يرافقني في رحلة العودة إلى الفندق.
Mark Riccobono: Yes.
مارك ريكوبونو: نعم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
DH: So since we started this project,
دنيس كونج: منذ بدأنا هذا المشروع،
we've been getting hundreds of letters, emails, phone calls
لا زلنا نتحصل مئات من الخطابات ورسائل البريد الإلكتروني والمكالمات الهاتفية
from people from all around the world.
من أشخاص من جميع أنحاء العالم.
Letters thanking us, but sometimes you also get funny letters like this one:
خطابات شكر لنا ، ولكن في بعض الأحيان تحصل أيضا رسائل مضحكة مثل هذه :
"Now I understand why there is Braille on a drive-up ATM machine."
"الآن فهمت سبب وجود طريقة برايل على أجهزة الصراف الآلي في اماكن القياده".
(Laughter)
(تصفيق)
But sometimes --
لكن احيانا --
But sometimes I also do get --
لكن احيانا احصل ايضا علي --
I wouldn't call it hate mail --
لا استطيع ان اقول انها رسائل بريد تحمل لي كراهيه --
but letters of really strong concern:
لكنها رسائل تحمل الكثير من الاهتمام:
"Dr. Hong, are you insane,
"د.كونج, هل أنت مجنون؟"
trying to put blind people on the road?
تحاول وضع الاعمياء علي الطريق؟
You must be out of your mind."
لا بد أنك فقدت عقلك."
But this vehicle is a prototype vehicle,
لكت هذه العربه فقط للتجربه,
and it's not going to be on the road
ولا يمكن أن تنزل إلى الطريق العام
until it's proven as safe as, or safer than, today's vehicle.
إلا إذا ما تأكدنا من سلامتها, على الأقل أكثر سلامه, ككل عربات اليوم
And I truly believe that this can happen.
وأنا متأكد من أن هذا سيحدث.
But still, will the society,
لكن, هل يستطيع المجتمع,
would they accept such a radical idea?
أن يتقبل هذه الفكره الجديده؟
How are we going to handle insurance?
كيف يمكن أن نتعامل مع التأمين؟
How are we going to issue driver's licenses?
كيف يمكن أن نستخرج رخص القياده؟
There's many of these different kinds of hurdles besides technology challenges
هناك الكثير من هذه العقبات بجانب عقبات التكنولوجيا
that we need to address before this becomes a reality.
التي يجب علينا التعامل معها قبل أن يصبح الحلم حقيقه.
Of course, the main goal of this project
طبعا, الهدف الرئيسي من هذا المشروع
is to develop a car for the blind.
هو تصميم سياره للكفيفين
But potentially more important than this
لكن حقيقه الأكثر أهميه من ذلك
is the tremendous value of the spin-off technology
هو القيمه الامحدوده من عملية التطبيق التكنولوجي
that can come from this project.
التي يمكن الحصول عليها من هذا المشروع
The sensors that are used can see through the dark,
المجسات المستخدمه يمكنها الرؤيه في الظلام
the fog and rain.
في الضباب وفي الأمطار.
And together with this new type of interfaces,
وجميعها مدمجه مع هذا النوع الجديد من التداخل,
we can use these technologies
يمكننا إستخدام هذه التكنولوجيات
and apply them to safer cars for sighted people.
وإضافتها إلي السيارات العاديه لجعلها أكثر أمان.
Or for the blind, everyday home appliances --
أو للاشخاص غير المبصرين, كل الادوات الكهربيه في المنازل
in the educational setting, in the office setting.
في الأدوات التعليميه, في أدوات المكاتب
Just imagine, in a classroom a teacher writes on the blackboard
تخيل فقط, في الفصل الأستاذ يكتب علي السبوره السوداء
and a blind student can see what's written and read
ويمكن لطالب غير مبصر أن يري ويقرأ ما يكتب الأستاذ
using these non-visual interfaces.
بإستخدام هذه الوسائط غير المرئيه
This is priceless.
هذا لا يقدر بثمن
So today, the things I've showed you today, is just the beginning.
اليوم, الأشياء التي أريتكم إياها, فقط البدايه.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)